Guide to the Sanderson, Maj. Winslow F. Papers, 1829-1880 MS 245
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Major Winslow F. Sanderson Papers
1829-1880
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Sanderson, Winslow F.
MS 245
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder of 32 items)
This collection consists of letters and documents relating to the life and death of Major Winslow (W.F.) Sanderson. Many of the documents concern the death of Major Sanderson, but two of the letters were written by him from Mexico in 1847. Other correspondence relates to his widow succeeding in securing a military pension, and two U.S. House of Representatives bills concerning the pension.
Biographical / Historical
Major Sanderson was a mounted rifleman in the U.S. Army who served on the western frontier and then in the Mexican War. In the summer of 1853, while awaiting a steamer to Galveston, he contracted yellow fever. After a time he seemed recovered, and proceeded to Galveston, where he suffered a relapse of the fever and died.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of letters and documents. Two of the letters were written from Mexico in 1847. Many of the documents concern the circumstances of his death, the disappearance of a large sum of cash from his person, and the money owed to the landlord of the Palmetto House where he was staying. There are also letters to the doctor who treated him and to the undertaker. Other correspondence concern debts owed by the major for military equipment, etc. There are also letters from his widow endeavoring to secure a military pension, in which she finally succeeded, and two House of Representatives bills concerning the pension.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased with Friends of Fondren funds on November 19, 1974.
General
Portions of this collection are available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/37264
Index Terms
Subjects
Military
Document Types
letters (correspondence)
- Series I: Letters and documents, 46083
  - Ms. H. Thayer to W.F. Sanderson, July 29, 1829, 46115 (Letter 1)
  - Invitation from Mrs. Ferris to unknown, August 26, 1841, 46114 (Letter 2)
  - Receipt form E.J. Hanford to W.F. Sanderson, April 8, 1846, 46113 (Letter 3)
  - Unknown (Adjutant General) to W.F. Sanderson, June 1, 1846, 46112 (Letter 4)
  - W.F. Sanderson to unknown, May 7, 1847, 46111 (Letter 5)
  - W.F. Sanderson to Francis Sanderson, October 32, 1847, 46110 (Letter 6)
  - Plan of Navy Yard, Memphis, Tennessee, October 1, 1848, 46109 (Letter 7)
  - Gen. Bootes to unknown, September 3, 1850, 46108 (Letter 8)
  - Receipt from unknown to W.F. Sanderson, November 27, 1852, 46107 (Letter 9)
  - S. Cooper to W.F. Sanderson, May 12, 1853, 46106 (Letter 10)
  - Receipt from unknown to W.F. Sanderson, June 29, 1853, 46105 (Letter 11)
  - S. Cooper to W.F. Sanderson, July 8, 1853, 46104 (Letter 12)
  - T.S. Simpson to W.F. Sanderson, August 31, 1853, 46103 (Letter 13)
  - J.E. Rump to Isaac Thayer, October 19, 1853, 46102 (Letter 14)
  - Unknown to Son Re: death of W.F. Sanderson, October 19, 1853, 46101 (Letter 15)
  - J.E. Rump to Isaac Thayer, October 23, 1853, 46100 (Letter 16)
  - Isaac Thayer to D.G. Twiggs, October 23, 1853; and D.G. Twiggs to Isaac Thayer, November 7, 1853, 46099 (Letter 17)
  - T. Ginnsley to Mrs. W.F. Sanderson, November 21, 1853, 46098 (Letter 18)
  - Isaac Thayer to Ms. Sanderson, January 28, 1853, 46097 (Letter 19)
  - Receipt from unknown to estate of Major Sanderson Re: coffin for W.F. Sanderson, February 28, 1854, 46096 (Letter 20)
  - Receipt from unknown to T.M. Armstrong Re: Grave for W.F. Sanderson, March 1, 1854, 46095 (Letter 21)
  - Receipt from A. Stanwood from Estate of W.F. Sanderson, March 1, 1854, 46094 (Letter 22)
  - S. Briggs and Charles Daniel to Misses Armstrong, March 1, 1854, 46093 (Letter 23)
  - Receipt from unknown to Estate of W.F. Sanderson, March 21, 1854, 46092 (Letter 24)
  - M.M. Potter to Ms. M. Sanderson, July 2, 1854, 46091 (Letter 25)
  - O. Worthington to U.S. Congress Re: Sanderson Memorial, July 9, 1854, 46090 (Letter 26)
  - Receipt from John Knop to Mrs. M. Sanderson, April 8, 1859, 46089 (Letter 27)
  - J.M. Armstrong to James D. Cleveland (U.S. Commissioner), March 26, 1860, 46088 (Letter 28)
  - Report by U.S. House of Representatives Re: Pension for Mrs. M. Sanderson, March 30, 1860, 46087 (Letter 29)
  - Bill by U.S. House of Representatives granting Pension to Mrs. M. Sanderson, March 30, 1860, 46086 (Letter 30)
  - Unknown to Frances William, August 27, 1880 (letter incomplete), 46085 (Letter 31)
  - Unknown to unknown, no date (letter incomplete), 46084 (Letter 32)